Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 4 of our 10
day Lipreading Challenge,
designed to help you develop and
practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career, your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and
tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity to relationships
in all areas of your life.
Before we get started with our
lip reading practice today,
I wanted to tell you about a way
to teach the people in your life
to speak more clearly
so that you can read their lips more easily.
A client once said to me,
if everyone talked like you,
I wouldn't have any problems with my hearing!
Hearing care professionals do tend to speak very clearly.
It's one of the occupational hazards.
We also have battery stickers
anywhere and everywhere,
and we talk fairly loud to everyone.
I don't remember being taught
how to talk to people with hearing loss
in any of my Audiology courses.
It's something that we all
learned from experience.
In other words, people are teachable.
I would caution against asking
people to speak clearly,
most people have the perception
that they're already speaking clearly.
If they feel defensive,
they may not hear your message.
If there's a person in your life who talks way too fast or mumbles
or becomes practically inaudible
at the end of a sentence,
there's a way that you can
teach them to do otherwise.
It's called the chameleon effect.
The chameleon effect is at play
when you lean forward
because the other person leans forward.
We unconsciously and unintentionally
mimic people that we are interacting with.
We are also chameleons when
it comes to rate of speech,
accents, and just about any form of behaviour.
I suggest you say the sentences
from today's practice in the mirror silently.
Look at yourself as you're saying them.
How clearly do YOU speak?
The clarity of YOUR speech is what it's going to make the chameleon effect
work for you.
If someone's talking too fast, slow down your own speech.
Crisp up the consonants.
Pause between sentences.
Say each word.
Don't let your words run together.
If someone in your life
drops off at the end of sentences,
then emphasize the ends of your own sentences.
Finish strong.
The chameleon effect does not work on everyone.
I myself am very susceptible to it. I find myself mimicking others unintentionally, a lot.
I have linked an article from my website
about the chameleon effect
in the frame below the video.
I find it fascinating.
Okay let's get started on our
lip reading practice for today.
As always, the answers are in the
section below the video frame.
Allow yourself some time to get warmed up.
If you're having difficulty after the first
few sentences,
Stop.
Go to the section below the video frame
and follow the instructions on what to do
to make it easier.
Then make sure you come back!
I will say sentences with F and V sounds silently,
then I'll give you some context,
and again say it silently.
Are you ready?
Number 1
The context is: Don't worry.
Number 1 again:
Number 2
The context is: Where did all the grapes go?
Number 2 again:
Number 3
The context is: a wedding
Number 3 again:
Number 4
The context is: distracted driving
Number 4 again:
Number 5
the context is: a rite of
passage for many teenagers
Number 5 again:
Number 6
The context is: You're not alone –
40% of the population admits to this.
and again:
Number 7
The context is: this is something that
we couldn't do in the COVID pandemic.
Number 7 again:
Number 8
The context is: This is something I
really miss about living in the east
Number 8 again:
Number 9
and the context is: dangerous
conditions for a sport in Hawaii
Number 9 again:
Number 10
The context is: a schedule for
a popular mode of transportation
Number 10 again:
Can you let me know
in the comments section
if you find the context is helpful
in understanding what I've said?
The F and V sounds
have a great deal of variability
in the way that people say them.
Some people barely have the teeth over the lip.
If you're feeling keen,
you could ask the people in your life
to say the list of 10 sentences silently
so that you can get practice with other people.
Have them say one of the sentences
randomly (not in order)
and without the context
because you already know the sentences.
The advantage of group classes for lipreading
is that you get practice with different people.
We each have our own way of speaking.
I placed a link to my online
classes in this section below
so you can get more information about them.
So I'll see you tomorrow!
Tomorrow we're working on vowels. Yay!
Please like my video,
subscribe to my channel,
and share this with others.
I'd really appreciate it.
Bye!